Guide to the Mirra Ginsburg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Mirra Ginsburg Papers,
1910-1999
Ginsburg, Mirra.
20 linear ft. (38 document boxes).
Columbia University Bakhmeteff Archive Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
BA#0134
7447714
Biographical Note
Mirra Ginsburg (1909-2000) was born in Bobruisk, Russia (now Belarus). She attended schools in Russia, Latvia, Canada and the United States, where her family moved c. 1928. Throughout her long and prolific career, Mirra Ginsburg has worked as a researcher, freelance writer, editor, and translator from Russian and Yiddish. Despite the absense of any formal training, Mirra Ginsburg became a highly respected translator, an active member of professional associations, and a winner of numerous awards. Besides being a translator and editor of adult stories, anthologies and plays (including works of such authors as Singer, Platonov, Bulgakov, Remizov, Babel' and Dostoevsky), she was also recognized for her charming adaptations and siccinct translations of folktales for children.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, writings, research notes, notebooks, printed material, books, photographs and one audiotape
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 11 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Writings
Series IV: Background materials
Series V: Biographic Material
Series VI: PEN
Series VII: Writings by Others
Series VIII: Periodicals
Series IX: Audiovisual
Series X: Books
Series XI: Oversized
Subjects
Authors, Russian--20th century.; Ginsburg, Mirra.; Aitmatov, Chingiz.; Annenkov, I︠U︡riĭ, 1889-1974.; Belinkov, A. (Arkadiĭ), 1921-1970.; Chukovskiĭ, Korneĭ, 1882-1969.; Gulʹ, Roman, 1896-1986.; Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1904-1991.; Wilson, Edmund 1895-1972.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; American literature--20th century.; American literature--Translations.; Children's literature, American.; Children's literature, Russian.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Barbara Frenchi (niece) Donation, 11/2002.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  Series contains Mirra Ginsburg's original correspondence with prominent literary figures, primarily in Russian, with some English correspondence (most notably with I.B. Singer). Manuscript drafts included. Photocopies or typed copies of the same document are enclosed, but not cataloged separately. Documents are filed alphabetically by correspondent, then chronologically, with interleaved incoming and outgoing correspondence.
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Aitmatov, Chingiz, New York, NY, Nov. 1972 - Jul. 1982, (7 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 4p. ms. draft) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [Draft pages enclosed to Jun. 1975 and Apr. 1982 letters.]
  - Aitmatov, Chingiz to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Frunze, USSR, Jan, 1973 - Jun. 1975, (3 a.l.s., 3 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Aksenov, Vasilii, [New York, NY], Feb. 12, 1984, (1p. a.l.s.(draft)) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    [Re: Aksenov - see also correspondence with Schroeter, Leonard on Ozhog]
  - Aksenov, Vasilii to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Washington, DC, Feb. 24, 1984, (1p. a.l.s., 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Annenkov, Iurii (Yury), New York, NY, Apr. 1969 - Aug. 1970, (7 t.l.s. (carbon copies), 1p. notes) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [Notes enclosed to the first letter (Apr. 3, 1969)]
  - Annenkov, Iurii (Yury) to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Paris, France, Apr. 1969 - Jun. 1970, (4 a.l.s., 4 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Belinkov, A. (Arkadii), New York, NY, Aug. 1968 - Dec. 1968, (3 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 1 t.c. (from Crown Publishers)) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Belinkov, A. (Arkadii) to: Ginsburg, Mirra, New Haven, CT, Sep. 1968 -Dec. 1968, (2 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s., 2 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Brodsky, Joseph, New York, NY, Apr. 18, 1975, (3p. a.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Bulgakova, E. S. (Elena Sergeevna), New York, NY, May 1968 - Sep. 1969, (2 t.l.s. (carbon copies), 1p. notes) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bulgakova, E. S. (Elena Sergeevna) to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Moscow, USSR, Jul. 1968 - Aug. 1968, (1 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s., 2 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    [See also: Chukovskii, Kornei, letter from Sep. 25, 1968 (contains a note from Bulgakova, E. S.)]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Chukovskii, Kornei, New York, NY, Aug. 1965 - Dec. 1965, (5 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 7p. a. draft, 1p. notes, 1 clipping (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chukovskii, Kornei to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Peredelkino/Moscow, USSR, Sep. 1965 - Nov. 1965, (4 a.l.s., 4 envelopes, 2p. photostats of first 2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis to: Chukovskii, Kornei, New York, NY, Dec. 10, 1965, (1p. t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [Enclosed to Dec. 9, 1965 letter by Ginsburg]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Chukovskii, Kornei, New York, NY, Feb. 1966 - Nov. 1966, (5 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 4p. m. draft) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chukovskii, Kornei to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Peredelkino/Moscow, USSR, Feb. 1966 - Oct. 1966, (4 a.l.s., 4 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Chukovskii, Kornei, New York, NY, Feb. 1967 - Oct. 1967, (6 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 2p. notes, 1p. ms. draft) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chukovskii, Kornei to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Peredelkino/Moscow, USSR, Jan. 1967 - Nov. 1967, (5 a.l.s., 1 a.c.s., 5 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Chukovskii, Kornei, New York, NY, Jan. 1968 - Nov. 1968, (4 t.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chukovskii, Kornei; Bulgakova, Elena Sergeevna to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Peredelkino/Moscow, USSR, Jan. 1968 - Dec. 1968, (5 a.l.s., 5 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [Letter from Sep. 25, 1968 also contains a note from Bulgakova, Elena Sergeevna]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Chukovskii, Kornei, New York, NY, Jan. 1969 - Sep. 1969, (5 t.l.s. (carbon copies), 1 a.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chukovskii, Kornei to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Peredelkino/Moscow, USSR, Mar. 1969 - Sep. 1969, (4 a.l.s, 1 t.l.s., 5 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Chukovskaia, Lidiia Korneevna, New York, NY, Oct. 1969 - Jun. 1994, (2 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 1 a.l.s. (draft), 1 ms. draft) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chukovskaia, Lidiia Korneevna to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Moscow, USSR, Nov. 1970 - Aug. 1989, (3 a.l.s., 4 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Gul' (Goul), Roman, New York, NY, Apr. 11, 1967, (1p. t.l.s. (carbon copy)) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gul' (Goul), Roman Novyi Zhurnal to: Ginsburg, Mirra, New York, NY, Jun. 15, 1967, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Jaba (Velichkovskaia), Tamara Antonovna; New York, NY, Apr. 1968 - Mar. 1970, (4p. a.l.s. (carbon copies), 3 t.l.s. (carbon copies), 1p. t. draft, 1p. (2 copies) t. l. (translation)) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    [See also: Hoffman, Michael, re: copyright of works by Zamiatin, Evgenii]
  - Jaba (Velichkovskaia), Tamara Antonovna to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Paris-Vanves, France; Sep. 1968 - Mar. 1970, (3 t.l.s., 3 envelopes, 1p. (2 copies) t. l. (translation)) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    [a.l.s. from Hoffman, Michael to T. Jaba enclosed. (with typed translation)]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Karlinsky, Simon, New York, NY, Jul. 20, 1971; Nov. 7, 1971, (2 t.l.s.(carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Karlinsky, Simon University of California to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Berkeley, CA, Jun. 16, 1971; Dec. 8, 1971, (2 t.l.s. with holograph corrections, 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Karlinsky, Simon, New York, NY, Jan. 1972 - Nov. 1972, (6 t.l.s. (carbon copies), 1 a.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Karlinsky, Simon University of California to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Berkeley, CA, Feb. 1972 - Nov. 1972, (7 t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Karlinsky, Simon, New York, NY, Jan. 11, 1973; Apr. 19, 1975, (2 t.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Karlinsky, Simon University of California to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Berkeley, CA, Jan. 1973 - Mar. 1979, (5 t.l.s., 2 clipping with ms. notes, 5 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    [Includes clipping of article "Andrei Platonov" by Karlinsky in The New Republic, Mar.31, 1979]
  - Mamleev, IUrii to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Ithaca, NY, [Dec. 6, 1978], (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra re: Mamleev, IUrii, New York, NY, Dec. 10, 1981, (1p. t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Morrison, Toni; New York, NY, Jan. 3, 1977; Feb. 9, 1977, (2 t.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    [re: Dead Fiddler anthology; Amalrik, Gyizel;]
  - Morrison, Toni; Random House to: Ginsburg, Mirra, New York, NY, Jan. 7, 1977; Jan. 31, 1977, (1 t.l.s., 1 t.l.(signed by secretary)) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Obukhova, Lidiia, New York, NY, Sep. 26, 1975, (3p. a.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Obukhova, Lidiia to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Moscow, USSR, Dec. 29, 1975, (1 a.p.c.s., 1 business card, 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Proffer, Carl, New York, NY, Dec. 1971 - Jan. 1974, (4 t.l.s. (carbon copies), 1p. t.l.s. (draft)) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    [Re: Annenkov, Yuri; Bulgakov, Mikhail; Maramzin, Vladimir; Chukovskii Family.]
  - Proffer, Carl Ardis Publishers; Russian Literature Triquarterly to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Ann Arbor, MI, Nov. 1971 - Jan. 1975, (6 t.l.s., 4 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    [Re: Annenkov, Yuri; Bulgakov, Mikhail; Chukovskii Family. Enclosed: Ardis printed materials, including copy of Russian Literature Triquarterly, Dec. 18, 1974 on Maramzin, Vladimir.]
  - Roziner, Feliks to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Boston, MA, [Oct. 1986], (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    [Removed from the book by F. Rosiner, V Domike Starogo Musykanta (see Books)]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Sapgir, Genrikh, New York, NY, Feb. 2, 1995, (2p. a.l.s. (carbon copies), 5p. ms. draft) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sapgir, Genrikh to: Ginsburg, Mirra, [Moscow, Russia], Feb. 11, 1995, (1p. t.l.s., 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Singer, Isaac Bashevis, New York, NY, Aug. 1959 - Nov. 1979, (4 t.l.s. (carbon copy), 1p. t.l. with ms. notes) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Maiami Beach, FL; Oberlin, OH; Aug. 1959 - Jul. 1966, (7 a.l.s., 6 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Sollogub, Natalia, Mar. 1967 - Dec. 1967, (5 a.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sollogub, Natalia to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Paris, France, May 5, 1967, (1 a.l.s., 1 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    [Enclosed: photocopy of letter by MG to Zamiatina, Liudmila of Mar. 12, 1965.]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr Isaevich, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.l.s. (draft)) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Struve, Gleb, New York, NY, Nov. 1967 - Aug. 1969, (5 t.l.s. (carbon copies)) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Struve, Gleb University of California to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Berkeley, CA, Oct. 1967 - Feb. 1975, (8 t.l.s. with ms. corrections, 1 a.l.s., 1 a.p.c.s., 9 envelopes, 4p. clipping with ms. note) (Box 1, Folder 27)
    [Re: Bulgakov, Mikhail; Platonov, Andrei; Belinkov, Arkadii; Kosterina, Nina. Enclosed: article "The Re-emergence of Mikhail Bulgakov", in The Russian Review, July 1968.]
  - Wilson, Edmund; to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Wellfleet, MA, Dec. 16, 1967, (1p. t.l.s., 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    [re: Singer, I. B.]
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Zakhoder, Boris Vladimirovich, New York, NY, Apr. 1987 - Feb. 1988, (2 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 4p. ms. drafts & notes) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Zakhoder, Boris Vladimirovich to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Bolshevo (Moskow Region), Russia, May 1987 - Jun. 1988, (3 t.l.s., 1 a.p.c.s., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Zamiatina, L. N., New York, NY, Sep. 1962 - Nov. 1963, (5 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 2p. ms. drafts & notes) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Zamiatina, L. N. (Liudmila Nikolaevna), to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Paris, France, Sep. 1962 - Nov. 1963, (3 a.l.s., 1 t. l. (translations of Sep. 27, 1962, Mar. 19, 1965), 1 t.l.s. (includes statement giving MG rights to use Zamiatin's works for anthology), 3 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra to: Zamiatina, L. N., New York, NY, Jan. 1964 - Mar. 1965, (6 a.l.s. (carbon copies), 1 t.d., 6p. ms. notes & drafts) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Zamiatina, L. N. (Liudmila Nikolaevna), to: Ginsburg, Mirra, Paris, France, Feb. 1964 - Mar. 1965, (5 a.l.s., 2 t.d.s., 4 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  Russian and English.
  - Subseries II.1: Prominent Individuals
    Incoming and outgoing high-volume (over 5 items) correspondence with friends, family, and colleagues. Photos separated, paper enclosures kept on file. Folders arranged alphabetically by personal name, correspondence within folder arranged chronologically.
    - Allworth, Edward Columbia University - Program on Soviet Nationality Problems, New York, NY, Jan. 1972 - Dec. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Belinkova-IAblokova, Natalia, Washington, DC; Monterey, CA, Oct. 1972 - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      [Includes open letter by Belinkova to Raisa Orlova re: Belinkov, Arkadii]
    - Blake Hill, Patricia, New York, NY, Jan. 1960 - Mar. 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      [Includes enclosed The Journey (translation by Mirra Ginsberg of short story by Babel', Isaac) typescript edited by P. Blake Hill]
    - Bokelman, Judith; Bokelman, Rinus, Charlotte, NC, Apr. 1975 - Jul. 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Caplan, Minnie, Orangeburg, NY, May 1932 - Apr. 1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Carvajal, Shesha, Santiago, Chile; Berkeley, CA, Nov. 1957 - Jul. 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6 - 8)
    - Christesen, Nina Mikhailovna University of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, Mar. 1969 - Oct. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chukovskaia, E. TS. (Liusha), Moscow, Russia, Nov. 1969 - Jan. 1999 (Box 2, Folder 10 - 12)
    - Congrat-Butlar, Stefan, Brooklyn, NY, Feb. 1967 - Mar. 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Daniels, Winnie, n.p., Feb. 1931 - Jan. 1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fanger, Don, West Newton, MA, Nov. 1970 - Dec. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fedoulova (Touja), Roza, Toulouse, France, Feb. 1980 - Jul. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fibich, Judith; Fibich, Felix, Jerusalem, Israel; Chicago, IL, [Jun. 1969] - Nov. 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ginsburg, Bronia, New York, NY; Hunter, NY; Rockville, MD, Jul. 1949 - Sep. 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6 - 7)
      [Mother]
    - Ginsburg (Berkovitz), Lea (Lily), Silver Spring, MD, Sep. 1935 - Sep. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      [Sister (10 years junior, married Jack Berkovitz)]
    - Ginsburg, Lea (Lina) and Lev (Leva), Riga/Libava, Latvia; Paris, France, Nov. 1925 - Apr. 1934 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      [School friends from Libava]
    - Handelman, Jeannette, Newark, NJ; Chicago, IL, Dec. 1931 - Apr. 1934 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      [Also includes a letter from Norman [Handelman], and drafts of Mirra's letters to mutual acquaintance Patsy]
    - Hoffman, Michael A. Agence Hoffman Attorney for heirs of Zamiatina (Mrs. Jaba and Mrs. Sollogub) re: copyright to works of Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich, Paris, France, Apr. 1967 - Mar. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      [See also Jaba, Tamara; Sollogub, Natalia, Zamiatina, Liudmila]
    - Kern, Gary Princeton University; University of Rochester, Princeton, NJ; Rochester, NY, Dec. 1967 - May 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Klimovitskaya, Polina, New York, NY; Hanover, NH: Madrid, Spain; Lisboa, Portugal, Jul. 1977 - 1994] (Box 4, Folder 2)
      [enclosed - draft of dissertation on Petrushevskaia, Liudmila]
    - Lights, Judy, NY, Apr. 1931 - Apr. 1933 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Litvinova, Tania, Moscow, USSR, Nov. 1969 - Feb. 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      [Friend of Chukovskii family]
    - Lurie, Frieda, Moscow, USSR, Dec. 1967 - Oct. 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - McCleland, Bertha, Quebec, Canada, Mar. 1927 - May 1929 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Rosenthal, Raymond, New York, NY, May 1984 - Aug. 1984 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      [re: Babel's Zakat]
    - Shane, Alex University of California; SUNY, Davis, CA; Albany-Gilderland, NY, Dec. 1967 - Feb. 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Shindel, Morton, Weston Woods, CT, Nov. 1969 - Feb. 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Slobin, Greta Wesleyan University, Middletown, CT, Dec. 1975 - Feb. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Spitz, Sheryl, Washington, DC, Nov. 1978 - Oct. 1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Stuhlman, Gunther Contains correspondence, book and translation contracts, enclosed letters to Stuhlman from the third parties re: MG's books, New York, NY, Nov. 1960 - May 1975 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      [Ginsburg's literary agent.]
    - Taylor, Bonnie Highsmith re: copyright of MG fairy tales. Includes notes and drafts, Lebanon, OR, Feb. 1992 - Feb. 1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      [See also Flower, Mary.]
    - Vasil'ev, Mikhail (Vassilieff, Michel), Paris, France, Apr. 1969 - Apr. 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Wigley, Eve, Villequier, France, Nov. 1980 - Nov. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Wolff, Nancy Cavallo & Wolff: Attorneys at Law re: Philomel Books, New York, NY, Jul. 1992 - Dec. 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - [Zimmermann], Gunther, [Frankfurt am Maine], Germany, Jan. 1958 - Sep. 1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.2: Organizations
    Correspondence with publishers, professional and funding organizations, includes enclosures, such as book contracts, royalty statemtents, book reviews, publishers booklets and catalogs, notes and letter drafts by MG, proofs and illustrations. Folders arranged alphabetically by company name, correspondence within folder - in chronological order.
    - Gostautas, Stasys American Litarary Translators Association (ALTA), Croton-on-Hudson, NY, Apr. 1982 - Mar. 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Solov, Liuba Amrus Literary Agency includes book report on Tsvetaeva, Marina, My Pushkin, New York, NY, Jan. - Mar. 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ardis Publishers (Box 1, Folder 21)
      [Filed under Cataloged Correspondence - Proffer, Carl]
    - Aiken, Paul; Pallante, Maria; Stout, Rex Authors Guild, Inc. re: Philomel Books (Clay Boy); re: Eridanos/Marsilio (Lieutenant Kije), Apr. 1970 - May 1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Douglas, John; Moldow, Susan; Rashbaum, Beth Avon Books re books: Obukhova, Lidiia, Daughter of Night; Zamiatin, Evgenii, We; New York, NY, Oct. 1981 - Jan. 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Armstrong, Gregory; Burbank, Toni; Murphy, Patricia Bantham Books Zamiatin, Evgenii, We; Dostoevskii, Fedor, Notes From Underground; Anthology The Dead Fiddler (rejected), New York, NY, Mar. 1969 - Mar. 1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Gill, Keith Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC) re: radio production of Bulgakov, Fatal Eggs, Toronto, Canada, Apr. 1984 - Jan. 1985 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Wilkin, Refna Coward, McCann & Geoghan, Inc. (Putnam Publishing Group) The Magic Stove, New York, NY, May 1981 - Dec. 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Brooks, Donna; Gipson, Morrell; Sawicki, Norma Jean; Crown Publishers, Inc. Diary of Nina Kosterina; Russain and regional folk and fairy tales (Fox and the Hare, Master of the Winds, the Kaha Bird, How Wilka Went to Sea, etc.); Aitmatov, Chingiz, The White Ship; Chukovskii, Korney, Ookie-Spooky; Suteyev, Victor, misc. tales., New York, NY, Oct. 1967 - Feb. 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1 - 3)
      [Includes photocopy of letter from I.B. Singer to M. Gipson re: Fox and the Hare, Nov. 11, 1969]
    - Fogelman, Phyllis G.; Gavril, Jean; Johnson, Mary Parke Dial Press Fairy Tales (One Trick Too Many), Obukhova, Lidiia, Lilith (rejected), New York, NY, Jun. 1969 - Apr. 1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Macrae, John III; Skedgell, Marian E. P. Dutton & Co. Platonov, Andrei, Foundation Pit; Platonov, Andrei, Chevengur (Book Report by MG)), reports on other works of Soviet fiction by MG., New York, NY, Jan. 1969 - Nov. 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Garcia de Oteyza, Juan; Phelan, Lisa; Eridanos Press, Inc; Marsilio Publishers Corp. Tynianov, IUrii, Leitenant Kije/Young Vitushishnikov. Includes photocopies of letters by Sir Isaiah Berlin & others re: Tynianov's book, Hygiene, CO; Boston, MA; New York, NY, Aug. 1988 - Jan. 1994 (Box 6, Folder 6 - 7)
      [Eridanos was acquired by Marsilio in 1991.]
    - Bobko, Jane; di Capua, Michael; Meiselas, Nancy; Meyer, John Farrar, Straus & Co; Farrar, Straus & Giroux, Inc. Book rejections, correspondence re: Chukovskaia, Lidiia Korneevna, Pamiati Detstva., New York, NY, Sep. 1949 - Aug. 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Mainiero, Lisa Frederick Ungar Publishing Co, Inc. Article on Zamiatin for Encyclopaedia of World Literature, New York, NY, Apr. 1970 - May 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Caldwell, George; Keene, Frances, Miller Jo An; Morley, Perry; Funk & Wagnalls Fairy Tales [rejected]; Bulgakov, Mikhail, Life of Monsieur De Moliere; New York, NY, Feb. 1968 - Jan. 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Hirschman, Susan; Shub, Elizabeth (Libby) Greenwillow Books (William Morrow & Co.) Tales: The Strongest One of All; Good Morning, Chick; Little Rystu; Fisherman's Son; The Night It Rained Pancakes; Across the Stream; Where Does the Sun Go at Night? The Sun's Asleep Behind the Hill; etc, many rejected., New York, NY, Mar. 1976 - Aug. 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4 - 6)
    - Braverman, Harry; Meeker, Marilyn, Seaver, Richard Grove Press Bulgakov, Mikhail, (Master and Margarita, Flight, Bliss, Heart of the Dog, [Fatal Eggs]). Book reports on Annenkov, UIrii; Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich; Kuzmin, Mikhail; Modern Russian Short Stories; Platonov, Andrei, Olesha, IUrii; Vosnesenskii, Andrei; AmalÂ´rik, Andrei., New York, NY, Mar. 1967 - Jun. 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Decter, Jacqueline Harcourt Brace Jovanovich The Chinese Mirror, New York, NY, Apr. 1971 - Mar. 1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Ignatowicz, Nina; Lindley, Frances; Shub, Elizabeth (Libby); Zolotow, Charlotte Harper & Row, Publishers, New York, NY, Jan. 1965 - May 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Wang, Arthur W. Hill & Wang, Inc Book report: Boguslavskaia, Zoia, I Zavtra; Russia's Other Writers, Russian poetry., New York, NY, Oct. 1967 - Oct. 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Chaikin, Miriam; Cheshire, Mark; Exman, Wallace (Wally); Kroll, Steven; Macrae, John III; Holt, Rinehart, & Winston The Ultimate Threshold (Soviet Science fiction); Regional Folk Tales, New York, NY, Jun. 1967 - Aug. 1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Gallman, John; Rabinowitch, Janet Indiana University Press Bulgakov, Mikhail, (Master and Margarita, Life of Monsieur de Moliere), Bloomington, IN, Aug. 1973 - Dec. 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Eisele, Elizabeth (Betsy); Stevenson, Dinah J. B. Lippincott Co. Twelve Clever Brothers, other tales rejected, New York, NY, Nov. 1978 - Apr. 1981 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Larkin, Phyllis; Shub, Elizabeth (Libby); Macmillan & Co. Obukhova, Lidiia, Daughter of Night; Suteyev tales; The Air of Mars Anthology, New York, NY, Dec. 1968 - Nov. 1992 (Box 7, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Ooms, Alexander National Endowment for Humanities (NEH) Creative Writing Fellowships, 1994-1995 - applicants texts and reviews by MG, Washington, DC, Aug. 1992 - Sep. 1994 (Box 8, Folder 7 - 8)
    - Glassgold, Peter New Directions Bulgakov, Mikhail, ( Flight, Bliss, Life of Monsieur de Moliere)., New York, NY, Jun. 1950 - Jul. 1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Brown, Francis New York Times Book Review re: Bulgakov, Mikhail, Master and Margarita translations; Zamiatin, Evgenii, New York, NY, Mar. 1967 - Aug. 1983 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Harris, Susan; Yost, Lee Prater Northwestern University Press A Soviet Heretic: Essays by Yevgeniy Zamyatin, Evanston, IL, Jun. 1991 - Apr. 1992 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Cloud, Robert Panteon Books re: Razgon, Lev, Memoirs, New York, NY, Nov. 1990 - Dec. 1990 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Friedlander, Christine; Glassgold, Peter; Mihalski, Kirsten; Morrone, John PEN American Center re: PEN Translation Committee; PEN Translation prize, New York, NY, Feb. 1971 - Mar. 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)